Right.
So yes uh the suta for u today well the
two sutas actually it's 4524
and then the other one will be on gutra
557. So um it says this one's very short says
So um it says this one's very short says
um at savati
the Buddha was addressing the bus and he
said because whether for a lay person or
for one gone forth I do not praise the
wrong way whether it is a lay person or
one gone forth uh who is practicing
wrongly because of an undertaking the
wrong way of practice he does not attain
the method the dharma that is wholesome
in other words he does not develop the
right view he does not become a sapana
and what because he's the wrong way.
It's the wrong view, wrong intention,
wrong speech, wrong action, wrong
livelihood, wrong effort, wrong leg
collection and wrong composure. This is
called the wrong way. And whether it's a
lay person or one gone forth who is
practicing wrongly, that is basically
the reason that their practice does not
lead to the attainment of the method and
that the dhamma to the dharma that is
wholesome. And then because whether a lay person or
And then because whether a lay person or
or a monk I praise the right way whether
it's a lay person or one going forth who
is practicing rightly because they
undertake the right way of practice and
they attain the method the dhamma that
is wholesome what because is the right
way it's the right view right intention
right speech right action right
livelihood right effort right
recollection right composure so that's
called the right way um so I thought
just to kind of um have this add this
suta just as a as a reminder
um because um I think even people that
who who have been listening to our talks
um even like regularly or or or over a
longer period of time I think even they
would um some of them might still have a
certain um
kind of tacit assumptions and notions
that um the the practice can be done
um the the practice can be done
differently uh if you're a householder.
So if you can't ordain for whatever
reason, you might feel like, well, you
know, I just can't help but be excused
from certain requirements. And this sort
of just cuts through all of that and
says it's simply not the case. Um so and
I think also like often what happens
um you know the five precepts the eight
precepts the celibacy or the kind of
non-selibacy uh the lines get blurred and then and
uh the lines get blurred and then and
then um and also thanks to the like
contemporary terravada not not making it
any clearer and kind of confounding the
matter further
um many people would even like read this
suta where clearly talks about the noble
path that it's the same for monks and
lay people without the difference. It
constitutes the right way or the wrong
way. But they would still kind of
believe, well, you know, I don't have to
do it to to such an extent. In other
words, I can get away without being
celibate or I can get away with with my
speech, you know, sometimes being kind
of um unh wholesome because that's just
the world we live in and so on. And uh I
mean again like nobody um nobody forces
you to to um
follow the noble ethal path or try to or
not. But if your goal is to practice the
dharma then there is no other way around
it. So it's like when the Buddha lists
the so what are the the the con the the
the const what constitutes the the noble
eight for path the right view which we
often talk about you know understanding
where the suffering comes from the four
noble truths there are many different
ways you could sort of um many different
aspects you could use to describe it but
it kind of leads to the same
understanding right intention right speech right
right intention right speech right
action right livelihood right effort
right composure so like right intention
like right thought, right intention was
always defined as um intention of
nonsensuality, intention of non- ill
will and non cruely.
So consequently that means that the
wrong intention is the intention of
sensuality. So if one is not practicing
the right intention, one is away from
the path.
One will not be able to attain the
method as the suta says. And that's just
to illustrate the point where people
think like um oh I can I don't have to
be celibate
uh and I can still practice the dharma
in the right direction. It's like if
you're not like if you cannot physically
withdraw yourself from sensuality
mentally will be inconceivable. It will
be inconceivable for you to be able to
mentally not have a sensual intention if
you are still physically engaging with
it. As I said many times, you know, the
simile of the sticks, like if the sticks
are still floating in the river, well,
no amount of your knowledge of how to
light the fire can make any difference
because they're simply soaking wet. So,
you need to take them out of the river
first. But even then, you got to wait
for them to dry. And that's this part of
drying up like your bodily behavior that
you would have stopped. Now, you have to
dry up your mind in regard to it. And
that's like this work that applies on
the level of right thoughts, right
intentions, right images as we as we
mentioned in our other talks on the
channel. So
the the the the whole training it's the
same. So whether you wear the robes or
not, if you want to practice the dharma,
uh you have to follow the same path. Um
and usually the difference that the
sutras uh kind of describe between the
lay people that uh practice the dharma
and the monks was not in how they
practiced was not in how they got to
there. As a matter of fact, there is not
a single suta that describes a lay
person's uh uh method of practice
independent of talking to the Buddha.
Basically like you know like oh the
Buddha said this is how lay people
should practice towards sotapati. No
such thing exists.
The sutas exist like this where there is
no differentiation between the method
and then the sutas exist of after they
became sapana and noble disciples and
kind of what they returned to or what
they chose to do whether to ordain
whether to pursue it further or they
were content with it. So and that's
that's the point here. So you realize
like the the the method of getting there
is the same according to the sutas. It
would make no sense to uh for lay people
that the method would that the
requirement for the method is lower than
for the monks because monk monks would
have already be given up the the lay
life the attachments the safety of
family which means surely then there
would be less requirements for the
monk's practice
and more for lay person's practice but
people today like to believe the
opposite. So the method was the same.
What was not the same was after you get
the right view, after you attain the
meth? After you understand the nature of
suffering, after there is no second
arrow hitting you,
are you content with that? Do you choose
to stop there and then okay, I'll go go
I'll go back. You might not have left
family, but you would have certainly
been internally withdrawn from it in
terms of practicing the noble path. So
you might choose to go back and support
and then look after people that depend
on you or for whatever reason or maybe
your health prevents you to live like a
monastic life or and so on. Uh but you
would know that that's now not the
practice. You know exactly what practice
was undertaken to get you to that method
to that understanding of the dharma that
is wholesome. And for many people that
might feel like more than enough and in
a way it kind of is obviously because
you know it's still like it's a major
leap. It's a bigger leap from a puja to
a sautapana than from a sautapana to
sakami in a way. So, so it was
understandable that even in the sutas,
the Buddha had to go around kind of
proddding and and and and sort of uh
acknow admonishing monks for not uh
practicing for arahandship for being
content with what they got because he
would say well no I would still go and
tell them you know don't be negligent
make the effort why because there is
still something that could be developed
there is still work to be done and
you'll regret it later because this
stood now in in your life this life in
particular uh it's it's the most optimal. In other
uh it's it's the most optimal. In other
words, the the the amount of effort that
you make in this life towards the dharma
practice has the uh highest benefit, has
the highest um highest gain. Um and
there was there was a sutra that
illustrates that. I think it was about
some a group of devas were talking to
the Buddhas or something and they were
they lived in such a realm where they're
all so uh confined, so packed up. He
said like I don't know thousands of them
would stand on would be like would take
the space of a a needle needle head and
yet they have no no will their minds are
immeasurable and doesn't matter how
squeezed they are basically the the
internally kind of they're un
unrestricted and then Sariputa said oh that's
and then Sariputa said oh that's
probably because you know they maintain
they practice that uh in that realm and
the deas corrected him and said actually
no please let him know that It's not
it's the practice we made while we were
humans. So in the human realm the effort
the little effort that they made
resulted being reborn in these in these
like obviously factually better places
where the mind is simply unconstricted
because the lift little what what might
feel like little effort now little
effort in the right direction obviously
not any effort uh but little effort in
the right direction can as the other
sutas say be like streams of merit. So
like you could spend your whole life
keeping the five precepts,
being generous, being helpful, being
kind and that's like the
base sort of threshold of meritorious
behavior. So but you still you wouldn't know
So but you still you wouldn't know
whether it will be enough or not or for
how long you will be benefiting from it.
But then the Buddha would go and explain
says but if one develops the right view
cultivates the right view even for the
duration of a finger snap or the actual
Janna withdrawal from sensuality
thoroughly thorough drying up even just
for a finger snap that's like the
streams of immeasurable merit.
So in other words, even you failing to
actually say uh get the right view or or
or become an arrogant practicing
according to the right method that he
describes in this suta will be
immeasurably more meritorious than any
merit that you do on a in a mundane
sense. So that's another kind of encouragement
So that's another kind of encouragement
as to well even if I fail my failure is
higher than not even trying basically in
terms of the the like the the pure
merit. Um
so that's for that suta and then kind of
it connects there's this this next suta
we want to do so it's 557 there's a part
about the action but we'll get to that.
So it says because these are the again
these are the five themes that should
often be reflected upon a woman or a man
householder or one gone forth again. So
no difference no difference in what you
got to what method you have to follow
what requirements you have to reach and
what reflections you have to do. What
five? A woman or a man, a um a householder
A woman or a man, a um a householder
or one gone forth should reflect that
I'm subject to old age. I'm not exempt
from old age.
A woman or a man in a household gone
forth should often reflect I'm subject
to illness. I'm not exempt from illness.
The third one is I'm subject to death.
I'm not exempt from death. The fourth
one is I must be and will be inevitably
parted separated from everyone and
everything dear and agreeable to me.
And then uh the fifth it's I am the
owner of my actions heir to my actions.
I have actions as my origin, action as
my relative actions as my resort. I will
be the heir of whatever actions good or
bad that I do. That's what we just
talked about. like even if you don't
necessarily uh well you won't be able to recognize
uh well you won't be able to recognize
the implications of your actions because
you simply don't see the bigger picture.
You know you can guess you can have an
inkling but the implications of your
actions are kind of infinite in that
sense. So it's like but you could know
whether your actions are rooted in
wholesome intentions
intentions that are aligned with the
noble path or the wrong intentions
intentions of sensuality intentions of
will uh that are not aligned with the
noble ethful path. So you don't need to
wait to to to um confirm the results of
your actions because obviously you know
your life will run out and the results
would have not necessarily been
depleted. But if you know that they are
rooted in uh u wholesome, if they're
rooted in the in the right intention,
you know that nothing bad can come out
of them even in 20 years time so to
speak because the the the direction is decided
because the the the direction is decided
in the beginning on the on the basis of
your intention. So no intention that's
rooted in unh wholesome can result in
wholesome. No intention rooted in
wholesome can result in unh wholesome.
Um and that just remains. So if it's if
it's a meritorious in a sense aligned
with the noble for path like in terms of
the the the the highest merit
um you don't even need to worry about
the implications and stuff because you
recognize that the roots of it are
rooted in wholesome even if the whole
world blames you for it. Say you want to
be celibate. um you want to withdraw
from sensuality as a lay person and
everybody around you is attacking you
for it and saying that you're you I
don't know you're mad you're um it's
unnatural you shouldn't be doing it it's
even if you don't yourself do not see a
direct benefit if you have enough faith
in terms of the like practice towards
the sapati outlined by the Buddha it
will be enough to keep you doing it and
it will be meritorious
in and of itself because Actually the
mind that wild animal is not being
polluted is not being constricted more
is not being sent down the pathways they
would then have these uh a lot kind of
worse uh repercussions and implications
because when people act out of
sensuality they act out of a constricted
context constricted perspective reduced
perspective um and uh and that's pretty much where
um and uh and that's pretty much where
all all the all of the world's problems
come from. I mean there's zuta I think
was it dig where the Buddha says it's
because of the sensuality
that I don't know husbands fight with
wives with sons sons with mothers um
sisters kings in the end like kings
fight with kings and everybody else
basically people resort to sticks
weapons killing each other lying all it
because of the sensuality because of
their desires a single reason for it
so so then the suta continues says for
the sake of uh for the sake of what
benefit Should a woman or man
householder or one going forth reflect
that I'm subject to age I'm not exempt
from old age
um says beings in the youth are
intoxicated with the youth and when they
are intoxicated with the youth they
engage in misconduct by body speech and
mind that's just exactly what I was
saying so
you already start with a reduced
perspective you already start with a
constricted uh context uh you're not
seeing the bigger picture not because
the bigger picture is sort of uh
mystically hidden away from you or
something. Uh it's because you are
ignoring certain aspects of it, usually
the unpleasant ones such as I'm subject
to old age. A young person does not like
to think, doesn't want, doesn't see a
point in thinking about them getting old
and how it will be.
And why don't they see a point? Because
they're drunk. They're drunk with the
youth. They they simply refuse to go in that
They they simply refuse to go in that
direction. So that's why the Buddha
needed to encourage these reflections
because by making an effort to think
those things like in that kind of
personally felt sense not just
abstractly contemplating old age or
something but in that personally felt
sense the Buddha needed to encourage
people to do it because it goes against
the grain of your whole being. It goes
against uh what you would want to do. It
goes against the alignment of your
desires and so on.
Sorry. Um, so it says, "But when one
often reflects upon these this theme,
the intoxication with youth is
completely either completely abandoned
or at least diminished." So in other
words, you are intoxicated because you
you refuse to think about the obvious
nature of your life, of your experience.
You refuse to uh stick to those uh uh
reflections. You refuse to cultivate
them. you refuse to allow them to kind
of sink in and be felt.
But if you do, well, the intoxication of
the youth cannot remain. It will be
undermined. It will be eroded and
eventually would evaporate or at least
diminish. So, so that's why the Buddha said it's
So, so that's why the Buddha said it's
for the sake of that benefit. So, it's
for the sake of basically uh sobering up
in regard to your life, in regard to the
permanence that that implies uh
ownership and everything else.
So the next one is for the sake of what
benefit should a woman or a man a
householder one gone forth reflect thus
I'm subject to illness I'm not exempt
from illness. This is the same. So when
beings are healthy they are intoxicated
with their health. In other words they
refuse to think about illness. They they
they um they kind of immediately default
back to that automatic conviction that
okay now that I'm cured I'll stay I'll
be healthy forever type of thing. even
if you know deep down of course I can't
I will get sick but I'll deal with it
when it comes I'll be okay so it's just
again like a carelessness that results
on account of being drunk with your
current health so you simply don't care
what happens to you in that sense and
because of that you refuse to think
about the obvious possibility of illness
coming at any given time
so in and of itself that in intoxication
wouldn't be a problem however as the
suta says and as anybody honest enough
would It will be impossible to not engage in
It will be impossible to not engage in
misconduct by body, speech and mind if
you're not intoxicated.
So it will be also impossible to not
engage in misconduct by body, speech and
mind. Um in other words, it's not
possible to to think that you can be
intoxicated but not engage in misconduct
by body, speech and mind. Intoxication
automatically leads to misconduct
whether you want it or not. intoxication
will imply it will get it uh will
basically manifest it the misconduct.
So that's why you could be making all
the effort you want to police your
conduct if you're not undermining the
intoxications. You're not uprooting
anything. Your misconduct is still
there. The framework for it is still
there waiting and sooner or later things
will manifest through it. In other
words, you're going to do one thing or
the other rooted in it. So that's why
yes you start with sense restraint and
precepts and withdrawal but it's these
reflections that then start to address
the roots of the problem. So if the
intoxication with health intoxication
with youth are removed well the great
basis for uh future misconduct for the
possibility of misconduct is removed. So
you are actually uprooting it.
So that is the benefit um that a woman
or man household or one go for should
reflect should often reflect on the own
illness. The third one is same uh about death but
The third one is same uh about death but
it's the same principle says one should
reflect that I am subject to death I'm
not exempt from death because during
their life lives beings are intoxicated
with their life and when they're
intoxicated they engage in misconduct by
body speech and mind and this one is
kind of probably the most offers the
most contrast is the most obvious that
when you genuinely contemplate death you
you immediately like kind of the the
undermine all of the desires that you
might still have towards anything that's
based on life or at least threaten them.
Everything will feel threatened if you
actually start contemplating death. Um
but that's only because there is still
intoxication and expectation and
assumption of permanence in regard to
life. You remove the intoxication.
Thinking about that will be the most
liberating thing
because it just reveals the that which
you would have already developed the
unownership uh burdenlessness
uh complete liberation of the mind. So
it's just aligned with it pretty much.
Death is aligned with nibbana.
Um so that's the benefit that one should
that's why a householder or a monk
should often reflect on these things.
Then the next one is uh in regard to uh
uh possessions. So it's like whether a
householder uh or a monk uh the benefit
for often reflecting that I must be
parted and separated from everyone and
everything dear and agreeable to me is
just to kind of undermine that dayto-day
um negligence uh willful ignorance of
taking up things taking up possessions.
While if you were to stop, think about
it, develop a context, you would
recognize that even things that are
yours are not yours really. Like you uh
the only time say you borrow something
from somebody. The only time you would
basically um believe or start believing
that you're an owner is if you forget
that it was actually borrowed or if say
you never knew. you you you thought it
was genuinely yours, but then you
discovered that no, you just borrowed
it. So, at any point of your usage of
the thing that you borrowed that you
know and you you you make the effort to
not forget that it's borrowed. At no
point would you then think, oh, I'm the
owner. I'm the master of this because at
any time the owner can come and ask for
it. So, you're still using it. You don't
need to destroy it or throw it away to
prove that it's not yours. you already
fully understood that it's not yours in
in its own nature. So that's kind of the
nature and that's sometimes like when
people find difficult to understand like
oh how is the arant
how does he operate on a day-to-day
basis when you know when anata is fully
developed nothing is his that's how so
he still has perceptions of things and
significance of the things and what they
can what those things can be used for
but at no point does he fall back into
that view which he's now incapable of
that he is the owner and those things
are like solely dependent for him and uh
um so whatever he engages with he
engages through that third person sense
in a way that this is someone's else
from the start throughout throughout the
duration of it. So that's why uh if you
frequently think and recollect that that
even things that are yours including
people are not yours cannot be yours
because at any given time they can be
taken away and and it's unfathomable for
you to be even able to like see how that
would happen or stop it or or be in the
way of it. Inconceivable you're just
going to be subjected to it one way or
the other. So it's not about see none of
these reflections are about oh I need to
think this through and arrive at some
sort of resolution.
Um
these reflections are not the management
of your anxiety of your fear of illness
of your fear of losing the loved ones.
They're actually supposed to bring it
up. And they're supposed to bring it up
because you're willingly choosing to
ignore it. And the benefits of bringing
it up is to train your own mind to stop
uh ignoring it to stop resisting it and
to stop taking it for granted because
that's where the sense of ownership
comes from. You can tell as the again
like the your commonplace sort of terra
instruction is like ah you practice
anata nothing is mine electrons are
constantly changing kalapas are
constantly flowing and so on. It's like
you could be repeating that paring that
for the rest of your life and no amount
of your ownership would have diminished
as a result of it
because the ownership diminishes when
that wild animal ceases to be wild. When
that wild animal starts to listen to
you, your own chitta. When your own
chitta cannot take possession of things.
So for that you need more than just
these these superficial mantras to
repeat yourself. For that you need these
reflections. For that you need to feel
the danger, the um the fear, the the uh
discomfort of the ideas of oo
separation, illness, death. And again,
not just so if I feel this long enough,
things will magically fall into place.
No, no, no. I bring these feelings up
because the mind doesn't want to look at
it. So I bring it up so that the mind
learns how to the animal learns to sit
down and calm down in face of these
things and not pressure me and push me
and go me and prod me to go back to
sensuality and provide it distraction.
So it continues thinking away from the
obvious nature of your experience
sickness aging death separation from
everything that's that's that's
agreeable and dear to you. So it's not
to like torture your mind either. uh
it's really the reference point for
these reflections and actually the more
you do these reflections the the the
clearer will be your mind will be
outlined as well because that's where
the resistance will be coming from in
regard to these things.
So that's why frequently recolor
recollecting this can lead to the right
view in and of itself obviously paired
with virtue and the prior withdrawal
from everything unh wholesome you should
have withdrawn as the previous suta
said. So um you you don't need to expect
like a perfect contemplation or perfect
results of this contemplation right from
the start. The point is to kind of
provoke the mind out of that sense of
indolence out of that sense of ignorance
um negligence and nonself awareness. So
it's probably going to be felt
unpleasantly in the beginning but again
you're not doing it for the sake of like
amplifying that discomfort or something
like because sometimes people might feel
okay so if I double down and increase
this pain of this fear somehow things
will be quicker not necessarily
the measure is the mind. So you you you
reflect these things on these things you
have maybe some feelings some resistance
come up and then you leave it there and
try not not sort of get distracted from
that because as the other sa say you
want to be furnishing your mind with
these perceptions. So the mind's looking
one way and that's the way you're
showing it these perceptions looks like
here's a bit of impermanence. Oh you
want to see this? Yeah you can look at
it but look at it through the
contemplation of illness. Look at it
through the contemplation of losing the
things that are dear to you. And that's
how the mind will then realize that it
cannot outrun it. That that also it will
realize that ignorance doesn't work.
That's why a vija feeds a vija as the
suta says. Basically through ignoring
you generally convince yourself that the
problem is gone. And again it's it's
it's on the level of chitta does that
already. So by by frequently
recollecting on these things it will
eventually sink down into the mind.
Chitta will understand that even when
you ignore stuff these things are there.
So that belief that your ignorance works
will be diminished.
Eventually it will be completely
uprooted if you stick to these
reflections. Like even monks were
encouraged to contemplate death,
contemplate these things because it's
like like the quickest way to basically
teach the mind what really needs to
understand and it's the quickest way
towards freedom. So that's that's kind
of the point that um through
recollecting these things not for the
sake of psychologizing your way out of
pain or or doubling down like through
the aesthetic like bearing of the pain
and just just bringing more of this
contact. No, no. just to like
provide let's say like that provide a
certain dis discomfort to your mind and
then leave it with it until it gets used
to it. So it doesn't need to be terribly
overwhelming or anything like that but
it needs to be there that that kind of
resonance needs to be there and it's not
going to be felt like resonance is going
to be felt like dissonance probably
because as I said all the desires and
everything else is leaning towards
looking away from it. So if you've
provided long enough if you reflect on
these things long enough not it's not
that you will become incapable of
forgetting things like like
forgetfulness is just the nature of uh
the five aggregates it's how things work
but you will be unable to maintain and
carry further the belief that
forgetfulness exempted you from these
contexts that connection will be severed and
that connection will be severed and
that's what means like Avij is destroyed
not that arant is constantly thinking
about everything all the time. No, it's
just that even when he forgets that's
forgetting happens within his
recollectedness recollectiveness of
certain contexts that no forgetfulness
can induce any old beliefs of oh I'm
actually uh separated from those
implications. Those things do not uh uh
uh apply to me anymore. And that's why
the power of distraction, the power of
sensuality, because for as long as that
belief, that connection with a video
exists, then giving in to those
directions of distraction, even if you
keep telling to yourself, oh, I know
this is unbeneficial
on the inside your mind, your chitta
still believes that it does actually at
least for that duration free you from
these pressures of these inevitable
contexts. Um, but once that belief is severed,
Um, but once that belief is severed,
well, your work's pretty much done. Then
you will not be able to return to
sensuality because the sole purpose of
the entire central domain was to
maintain that momentum of that belief
that makes you basically feel free from
the problems of these fundamental
existential nature.
Um, so that's the benefit of that. And
then what's the what's the benefit
because of which u a woman or man
householder one gone false should
reflect that I am the owner of my
actions add to my actions have actions
as my origin actions my relative actions
as my resort I will be there to whatever
actions good or bad there I do I already
said kind of talked about it in the when
we did the just now the previous the
first suta
it's basically recognizing that uh the
wholesome or unh wholesome or neutral
actions are determined by your
intentions So that kind of brings the weight of the
So that kind of brings the weight of the
responsibility on the intentions because
usually uh in the beginning the weight
on respons of the responsibility of
one's actions are pretty much on the
results of one of one's actions. So like
you know I'll steal for it and I'll lie
and I'll feel the weight of it only if I
get caught. That's how many people
operate. If I don't get caught, if I
don't obviously harm anybody, it's not
unh wholesome. they don't see it as a
problem and they'll do it. But if you
start recognizing that the action begins
with your intention means oh you're
already incurring a lot of unh wholesome
um including like the actual results of
those actions are already felt even if
you don't necessarily see them and those
results are felt on the level of that
wild animal.
So as I as I often say as I said in
those previous talks as well so might
everything might feel fine
um even for people that don't keep the
precepts you know it's not that they
that they're like unhappy or something
because of it. It's just that they're
going to pay a higher price and they're
already paying it without realizing
that. So it's like um when the when the
wild animal is allowed the wilderness
it's allowed to to um do what it wants.
It's not being tamed. You're basically
increasing its capacity for wilderness,
its capacity for being irrational and
crazy and wild and prone to passion,
which means when that animal turns
around and bites you, which it will when
illness happens, when you lose,
inevitably has to happen, it will bite
you a lot harder.
So the state of the mind of an untrained
mind, it's not a neutral, it's not like
a static thing. Okay, this is untrained
and no, it grows and it knows no limits.
So when the time comes when that mind
doesn't get what it wants, it will turn
against you and it will bite you a lot
harder, a lot more viciously. Uh it will
cause a lot more damage than the mind
that say was significantly tamed and
still turns around and starts blaming
you for something. And that's the
difference that I keep telling to people
even when you know when they when they
get when they're caught up in these
mental patterns of self-loathing and
blame and it's just with all this force
and power for years and they can't get
rid of it. That's the reason why
because your mind has no respect for
you. Has been allowed in the meantime
all this wilderness, all this access. So
its bite got stronger, its force got
even bigger.
If you take that away, no amount of your
traumas and stuff from the past and the
mind trying to revolve around it can hit
you as hard
because you're taking away the sail from
its wind. The sail from its wind, the
wind from its sail. Uh, and that's the
point. So it's not a it's not a static
thing just like black or white. It's
like your actions matter. Are you
feeding the wilderness, the craziness of
the animal, or are you reducing it? So
although it still hasn't turned around
to bite you, the fact is that you're
cultivating the wilderness of the animal
means you're already basically deciding
what type of bite it will be when it
happens. So in other words, the results
of your actions are already being
developed there even without anything
obviously palpable and so on at the
time. So that's why it's important to
always like I'm the owner of my actions
like I they cannot go to to anybody
else. They will remain bound with me and
this mind and and there is no third
option there. Basically it's just
there's no second option in that way. So
that's why these reflections are on the
same level the reflection about action
and the ownership and the roots of it
which is your intentions.
Uh that's why they're on the level of
contemplating sickness, aging, death,
separation and all of it. It's that
fundamental.
So then says the the noble disciple
reflects thus uh I'm not the only one
who is subject to old age. So basically
see you reflect like this
the way we described it will eventually
as I said outline your mind more and
more more simply through that sheer
gratuitous resistance of the mind in
regard to these contemplations
and then um that's that's pretty much
what will be like when you see your mind
that animal clearly when the a certain
layer of identification with it is uh is
is um abolished through that seeing it.
See through through perpetually not
seeing the animal through habitually not
seeing the extent the outlines the
limits of your mind that's the atavvada
the result of that is atavvada is not
your theoretical conviction that I am
self and so on no it's the symptom it's
the result of a of an underlying
ignorance uh looking past and nonrecognition of
uh looking past and nonrecognition of
what the chitta is. So if if you would
have been outlining it through precepts,
restraint and these recollections
frequently dwelt upon the chitta will be
seen and then whether you want or not
you will be unable to identify with it
and assume assume yourself as some sort
of external owner to the whole thing. So
atavvada will be gone. So that's why the
noble disciple once he's kind of
cultivated and established in these
recollections will then also know that
I'm not and will be able to remind
himself as well. I'm not the only one
who is subject to old age exempt from
old age. All beings that come and go
that arise and pass away they undergo
the same basically nature. They're
subject to old age rebirth and um birth
old age and not exempt from old age
subject to old age and nonexempt from
old age.
So he would often reflect on this theme.
The path is generated even clearer. U he
pursues it, develops it and cultivates
it and then the all the fats would be
abandoned. So this is like a condensed
way. See like uh you would have
contemplated enough that you're subject
to old age the mind would have been
outlined and so on. But now within that
say you would have abandoned atavada you
are a sautana but within that there is
still that sense of I am that still
lingers uh through some perversion of perception
uh through some perversion of perception
in regard to the ownership in regard to
permanence. So it's not on the scale of
a puja it's not on the extent of a of a
of a puja's mind who doesn't see any of
it. So he's like really subjected to the
whole thing but there is still uh
remnants the residues as the suta say
it's like you know puta would have been
stuck with stuck with a poison arrow
that's still like like um emitting
poison into the wound but a noble
disciple would have would have had arrow
pulled out but there is still now the
residual poison left. So then he needs
to follow a certain diet uh anoint the
wound clean it until that's gone as well
there secondary infections and so on and
that's what these recollections say so
the path will be generated in a sapana
the path that he knows
will be highlighted if he keeps
reminding himself of this oh this is
like again even even to the extent that
I understood and to the extent that I do
have a conceit of I am sep separate from
this person or that person. Well, to
that extent you kind of recognize as
well but this I am that might feel
separate to that subtler extent not like
augenous level of of conceit. Uh but
even that cannot be exempted from it
even that cannot not partake in the same
nature. So in other words it's just
practicing what other suta says a noble
disciple should practice not mine not
for me not I am. And he reminds himself
uh uh through these four five aspects of
sickness, aging, death, um uh losing
things that you're connected with and
that you are the owner of your actions.
So I'm not the only one I'm not the only
one subject to death. I'm not the only
one who must be parted and separated
from everybody. All beings that come and
go. So no exception basically. Not even
not even like in terms of the human just
in any realm in any shape or form this
is like inescapable which means any
lingering conceit of I am that to that
extent I might be separate a little bit
for a period of time you're not
even that's included in it and that's
what the noble disciple wants to be
practicing including the sense of
conceit the the little desires that he
still has left and so on reincing them
into this context until it fully
permeates all of the layers that are
there that need to be permeated and
that's why then all the fatters will
eventually be abandoned and the
underlying tendency completely uprooted.
So hardship and complete freedom. So the
suta finishes with these verses saying
world warlings putas are subject to
illness old age old age death and are
disgusted by other people who exist in
accordance with the nature. So they feel
like quite ir to to an irrational degree
in a sense to like a degree of madness.
They feel separated from the obvious
things that they see others go through
and they feel disgusted with them. So
that's how far gone they put. That's how
how how exempt from those things they
feel that they actually feel justified
in their disgust of that which is like
they're partaking in. So obviously a
noble disciple wouldn't be going that
far. But then he should remind himself
even further that even the slightest
disgust with what I perceive in others I
must reinclude myself in it. So until
there is no conceit left basically. So
if I were to be become disgusted with
beings who have such a nature that would
not be proper that would not be aligned
with the path basically since I I have
the same nature. So the Buddha says
while I was dwelling this having known
the state without acquisitions without
ownership he overcome all intoxications.
Intoxication with health, youth, life
and having seen security in runciation
means security in giving up sensual
desires. Zeal arose in me and I clearly saw
Zeal arose in me and I clearly saw
nibbana and recognized that he's
incapable of indulging essential
pleasure. That's what I said before. you
you you frequently recollect these
things. Um all those coverups that serve
as as maintenance of the belief in your
Avijia will become redundant because you
you would have destroyed the belief in
your vision. You whether I ignore this
or not the context remains the same. The
nature of what I'm subjected to remains
the same
and then the whole purpose of sensuality
is removed. And that's why he says like
once he clearly understood that he he
recognized that he's incapable of
indulging in such pleasures because
again the reason for them is gone.
Relying on this spiritual life never
will I turn back. So that
So that
concludes pretty much um these two
sutas.